Finding Aid for Michigan Student Assembly (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Student Assembly (University of Michigan) records
1975-2008
University of Michigan. Michigan Student Assembly
2010023 Bimu F13 2
The Michigan Student Assembly (MSA) is the official student government organization for the University of Michigan. Established in 1906, the student government now known as MSA has existed under the names the Student Council, the Student Legislature, the Student Senate and the Student Government Council. The MSA record group is comprised of annual reports, minutes, resolutions, organizational files, scrapbooks, and publications.
16 linear feet
8 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The main collection was received from the Michigan Student Assembly (donor no. 10,243 ) in August 2009. Some earlier material was received from the Student Activities and Leadership Office (donor no. 9058 ) in 2007.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open for research
The first student government at the University of Michigan was organized as the Student Council in 1906 by the Michigan Union. The Union itself had been organized in 1903 by students wishing to bring unity to an exponentially growing student body who had no common dormitory or social space.
The need for self-governance was recognized after the popularity of hair-cutting between men of warring classes came to a head with the assault of one individual in the library during daylight hours. The incident resulted in the expulsion of the ring leader; which was protested by fellow students. The faculty, concerned with what they saw as the general decline in the good conduct of the students, endeavored to intervene. According to the 1906 Michiganensian students felt that these issues, as student issues, should be dealt with through self-government and the Student Council was elected. The council is first mentioned in the September 1907 minutes of the Regent's Proceedings as, "men elected by the body of students to secure the wise management of their affairs." The Regents also commend them on stopping the "silly and sometimes dangerous amusement of hair-cutting," among other reforms.
The council moved toward formal organization when it successfully petitioned the regents for a budget of $150 for the 1912-1913 school year. Through the years, the government underwent several name reincarnations including the Student Senate in 1938 and the Student Legislature circa 1946. In December 1954, students voted 5,102 to 1,451 to restructure the student government and asked the regents to officially recognize the organization. At their December 1954 meeting, the Regents agreed to give the Student Government Council (SGC), as it was to be known, a two-year trial period. The first meeting of the SGC was held in March of 1955 where an eighteen member council was approved with the constitution of the Student Council serving as a temporary constitution during the trial period. In 1957, the regents approved the SGC as the, "official and authoritative voice of the University student community." The SGC was given the power to recognize student organizations; a power that had previously belonged to the University Senate Committee on Student Affairs.
Following a period of questioned voting practices and accusations of money mishandling; the SGC's reputation was in tatters amongst students and administration alike. Widespread call for reform resulted in the Central Student Judiciary Committee's January 21, 1976 decision to dissolve the SGC and to establish a new, restructured entity in its place to be called the Michigan Student Assembly (MSA). The Regents officially recognized MSA as the new student government at their September 1976 meeting. The MSA continues to serve as the central government of the students at the University of Michigan and to carry out its duties as outlined in its constitution dated March 2006 and quoted below. Further information about the Michigan Student Assembly is available via their website: http://www.msa.umich.edu/
For information regarding the records of earlier entities of MSA, see the finding aid for the Student Government Council records (University of Michigan) 1912-1975.
--------------------------------------------------------------
[Excerpt from MSA Constitution] D. Michigan Student Assembly. The Michigan Student Assembly (hereinafter referred to as "MSA" or "the government") shall consist of the Assembly, the Steering Committee and the Central Student Judiciary (hereinafter generally referred to as "CSJ" or "the judiciary"). MSA shall be the one central student government, and the representative and coordinating organization of the students of the Ann Arbor Campus of The University of Michigan.
Article II Assembly Powers and Functions Consistent with the limitations imposed in other sections of this Constitution, the governmental, representative, legislative, and coordinating powers and functions of the Assembly shall be as follows: A. Rules. T o make and sanction rules governing students. B. Dues. To levy dues and provide for their collection equally among all the students of the Ann Arbor Campus. The Michigan Student Assembly fee shall be considered to be dues. The Assembly shall not raise the level of the fee above a maximum limit approved by a vote of the student body. The fee at the time of the adoption of this section shall be the initial limit. All fees collected in excess of the fee limit shall be placed in a University account created for the sole purpose of holding such funds. These funds shall be appropriated upon a referenda that empowers MSA to utilize such funds. C. Appropriations. To appropriate monies collected under Article II, Section B, and all other sources of income. D. Lobbying. To lobby for the interests of students. E. Judicial Appointments. To appoint members of the Central Student Judiciary as provided in Article X of this Constitution. F. Projects. To originate student projects and activities. G. Recognition, Coordination, and Calendaring. To provide a system for the automatic registration of all groups meeting the definition of a student organization, to coordinate the activities of such organizations, to calendar or provide for the calendaring of student sponsored events, and to revoke recognition to groups not meeting those requirements. A student organization shall be defined as any group which has at least five students as members, has students or University Family Housing lessees as a majority of members, and which has University of Michigan students, Family Housing lessees, faculty, alumni, or staff comprising two-thirds of the groups' membership. Individual members of the group shall not benefit financially as a result of the groups' activities, for the group to be defined as a student organization. All groups meeting the definition of a student organization shall have the right to be registered, and shall be considered recognized upon registration. H. Elections. To conduct its own election and referenda among the student body, to provide for the manner of nominating candidates in its elections and to enact campus-wide regulations governing the conduct of its elections, campaigns, and related activity. I. Applying Bill of Rights. To apply the Bill of Rights contained in Article IX of this Constitution to all student bodies, all University bodies, and all its own operations. J. Appointments. To serve as the appointing body for selection of members of student committees, student representatives to outside bodies, except insofar as the Assembly may delegate this function, and to remove such appointees. The foregoing shall include, but not be limited to such all-campus bodies as the Board of Directors of the Michigan Union, the Office of Student Services Policy Board, the University Judicial system, the University Council, the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, the University Cellar Board of Directors, the committees of Senate Assembly, and all regental and presidential committees. K. Compiled Code. To establish a Compiled Code of legislation in order to exercise the powers and carry out the functions described herein. L. Summer Operations. To provide procedures for representation of student interests during the spring and summer terms.
The Michigan Student Assembly (MSA) record group is comprised of annual reports, minutes, resolutions, organizational files, scrapbooks, and publications produced by the Assembly, its committees, and its officers in official and unofficial capacities. The record group has eight series: Minutes, Reports, Records, Files, Student Legal Services, Visual Materials, Scrapbooks, and Publications.
Subjects:
College student government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Student Assembly.; University of Michigan. Student Government Council.; University of Michigan--Social life and customs--1971-1980.Social life and customs1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Social life and customs--1981-1990.Social life and customs1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Social life and customs--1991-2000.Social life and customs1991-2000.; University of Michigan--Social life and customs--2001-2010.Social life and customs2001-2010.
- Minutes, 1975-2008
  The Minutes series (9.0 linear feet) is arranged chronologically and spans the years from 1975 to 2008. The series houses the meeting minutes of the Michigan Student Assembly and its committees. Information within the minutes includes issues discussed by MSA, resolutions adopted, student organizations funded, as well as general business conducted by the assembly. Incorporated within the series is the last semester of minutes generated by MSA's predecessor the Student Government Council. These minutes serve to document the lead up to the government's reorganization.
  - September 1975-December 1983 (Box 1)
    (September 1975-January 1976 as the Student Government Council)
  - January 1984-November1987 (Box 2)
  - December 1987-July 1991 (Box 3)
  - September 1991-December 1995 (Box 4)
  - January 1996-April 1999 (Box 5)
  - April 1999-April 2002 (Box 6)
  - April 2002-March 2004 (Box 7)
  - March 2004-March 2007 (Box 8)
  - April 2007-February 2008 (Box 9)
- Reports, 1976-2004
  The Reports series (.5 linear feet), 1976 to 2004, is arranged alphabetically. The series contains annual reports prepared by MSA for submission to the Board of Regents. Other reports include those prepared for MSA in order to inform the Assembly concerning the university and its students. Information of interest includes MSA statistics, student organizations recognized, resolutions enacted, and goals met.
  - Department of Defense Sponsored Research at the University of Michigan, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Focus on Retention: A Report of the Recruitment, Retention and Graduation Project of the MSA, 1985 (Box 10)
  - MSA Annual Reports, 1978/79-1979/80; 1981/82-1987/88 (Box 10)
  - MSA Auditor's Report, June 30th, 1978 (Box 10)
  - MSA Financial Report, June 30th, 1976 (Box 10)
  - MSA, Inc., Student Legal Services and Ann Arbor Tenant's Union Combined Financial Report, 1989 (Box 10)
  - MSA Program Report and Fee Assessment Request to the Regents and Executive Officers of the University of Michigan (1985-1987), June 1985. (Box 10)
  - MSA Program Report to the Regents of the University of Michigan and Fee Assessment Request, June 1983 (Box 10)
  - MSA Semester-end Report, January 2002 (Box 10)
  - MSA Semester-end Report, January 2004 (Box 10)
  - MSA Semiannual Report, December 2001 (Box 10)
  - MSA Summary of Student Organizations Funded, 1998-2001 (Box 10)
  - MSA Year-end Report, April 2002 (Box 10)
  - MSA Year-end Report, March 2003 (Box 10)
  - Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center, 1985-1986 (Box 10)
  - South University Tear-gassing Incident of September 14th, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Student's Rights Commission Investigative Report on the University's Symbolic Structure Policy, 1991 (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Budget: A Report to the MSA, 1983 (Box 10)
- Records, 1976-1998
  The Records series (.75 linear feet) covers the years from 1976 to 1998 and is arranged alphabetically. Resources within this series include those documents generated by the MSA as a part of its official business or for internal use. Items of interest include the MSA Constitution and Compiled Code, procedure handbooks, forms, and guidelines.
  - Alcohol Awareness Week Information & Schedule, 1991 (Box 11)
  - All-Campus Constitution of the Student Body of the University of Michigan, 1976 (Box 11)
  - All-Campus Constitution of the Student Body of the University of Michigan, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Central Student Judiciary Trial, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Compiled Code Chapters 0-20, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Compiled Code Chapters 21-61, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Constitution and Compiled Code, 1987 (Box 11)
  - Constitution and Compiled Code, 1990 (Box 11)
  - Court of Common Pleas Trial Procedure Handbook -- Chapter 53 of the Compiled Code, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Elections, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Elections, 1991-1993 (Box 11)
  - E-mail Correspondence (Printouts), 1998 (Box 11)
  - Events and Funding Request Forms, undated (Box 11)
  - General Regulations Governing Student Organizations, 1976-1986 (Box 11)
  - Instructions for Student Organization Registration, 1986-1990 (Box 11)
  - MSA Handbook, 1991 (Box 11)
  - MSA Office Handbook, 1983-1985 (Box 11)
  - Proposals and Issues, 1983-1985 (Box 11)
  - Resolutions, 1991-1992 (Box 11)
- Files, 1976-2007
  The Files series (1.25 linear feet) encompasses the years 1976-2007 and is arranged alphabetically with the exception of one general file that appears first and holds miscellaneous file items. The series is comprised of files from MSA and those files generated in unofficial capacities including proposed amendments, funding applications, campus survey results, and reorganizations discussions.
  - General, 1983-1986; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Ann Arbor Tenants Union and Housing Board of Appeals, 1976-1986 (Box 11)
  - Budget Priorities Committee (BPC) Student Organization Funding, 1985-1986 (Box 11)
  - Code for Non-academic Conduct, 1984-1985 (Box 11)
  - Code of Student Conduct Review Committee, 1998 (Box 11)
  - Course Evaluation Committee, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Election's Office, 1989 (Box 11)
  - Film Group Scheduling, 1990 (Box 11)
  - Funding Applications and Grant Agreements (Samples), Winter 2004 (Box 12)
  - Funding Applications and Grant Agreements (Samples), Spring/Summer 2004 (Box 12)
  - Funding Applications and Grant Agreements (Samples), Winter 2005 (Box 12)
  - Funding Applications and Grant Agreements (Samples), Summer 2007 (Box 12)
  - GRIPE Proposal, 1985 (Box 12)
  - History Project and Documentation of Major Projects circa, 1951-2001; 2001 (Box 12)
  - Legal Services, 1983-1985 (Box 12)
  - Michigan Association of Governing Boards of State Universities (MAGB) Awards, 1998 (Box 12)
  - MSA Campus Survey and Results, 1988 (Box 12)
  - MSA Evaluations, 1983-1984 (Box 12)
  - MSA Fee Request, 1988-1989; 1996-1998 (Box 12)
  - MSA Internal Survey, 1989 (Box 12)
  - MSA Overview and Committees, 1990 (Box 12)
  - MSA Proposed Amendment, 1988-1989 (Box 12)
  - MSA Regental Mandate, 1986; 1989 (Box 12)
  - MSA Reorganization, 1985-1986 (Box 12)
  - MSA Retreat, 1985; 1987; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - MSA Steering Committee, 1985 (Box 12)
  - MSA Task Force, 1988 (Box 12)
  - MSA Transition and Committee Information, 1985-1986 (Box 12)
  - Michigan Union Student Organization Office Space, 1985 (Box 12)
  - Student Organizations and Contacts, 1978-1979; 1985-1986 (Box 12)
- Student Legal Services, 1979-1987
  The Student Legal Services series (.75 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and spans the years 1976 to 1987. It is comprised of materials regarding the Student Legal Services (SLS) a subsidiary organization of the MSA. The series houses the SLS's bylaws, minutes, files, and memorandum.
  - Amended Corporate Bylaws, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1980-1984; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Board of Directors Liability, Duties, and Responsibilities, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Board of Directors, Subcommittee Draft Report, 1981 (Box 12)
  - Budget and Finances, 1982-1984 (Box 12)
  - Memorandum, 1981-1987 (Box 12)
  - Parliamentary Procedure, undated (Box 12)
  - Participant Characteristics Report, 1985-1987 (Box 12)
  - Personnel Policies and Procedures, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Questions and Responses, undated (Box 12)
  - Reorganization Controversy, 1979-1984 (Box 12)
- Publications, 1976-1998
  The Publications series, 1976-1998, (1.5 linear feet) includes those publications produced by the MSA. The series holds the publications, directories, and newspapers published by MSA.
  - Advice, 1986; 1996 (Box 13)
  - Flyers and Handouts, 1978-1996 (Box 12)
  - MSA Handbook, circa, 1990 (Box 12)
  - MSA Campus Report (Box 12)
  - MSA News/Notes, 1983-1985 (Box 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1988-1990 (Box 12)
  - S.O.B.E.I.T, 1985-1986 (Box 12)
  - Student Organization Manuals/Directories, 1984; 1988/89; 1994/95 (Box 12)
  - MSA News, 1976-1978 (Box 13)
  - The Line, 1981-1982 (Box 13)
  - MSA News, 1982-1985 (Box 13)
  - , MSA Campus Report, 1985-1986; 1988-1990 (Box 13)
  - And Undated, MSA Times, 1997 (Box 13)
  - The Initiator, 1998 (Box 13)
- Visual Materials, 1976-2007
  The Visual Materials series (1.0 linear feet), 1976 to 2007, is arranged alphabetically. Presidential photographs is comprised of the photographs of past MSA presidents.
  - Presidential Photographs, 1976-2007
    - January 1976-March 1993 (Box 14)
    - March 1994-March 1997 (Box 14)
    - Fall 2007 (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks, 1975-2007
  The Scrapbook series, 1975-2007 (2.0 linear feet) contains scrapbooks maintained by the MSA beginning in 1975 and continuing through 2007. Included are clippings from the Ann Arbor News and The Michigan Daily about the Assembly.
  - 1975-1976 (Volume 1)
  - 1976-1977 (Volume 2)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 15)
  - 1978-1981 (Volume 3)
  - 1981-1983 (Volume 4)
  - 1983-1985 (Volume 5)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 15)
  - 1987-1989 (Box 15)
  - 1991-1992 (Volume 6)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 15)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 15)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 15)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 16)
  - 1997 (Box 16)
  - 1997-1999 (Box 16)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 16)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 16)
  - 2004-2005 (Volume 7)
  - 2005-2007 (Volume 8)